A Guide to the Rockefeller University records, President, Detlev Bronk, Biographical and Personal material FA964
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller University records, President, Detlev Bronk, Biographical and Personal material
1923-1976
Rockefeller Archive Center
Bronk, Detlev W. (Detlev Wulf), 1897-1975
Rockefeller University
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
FA964
3.08 Cubic Feet 7 boxes
7 boxes.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 303-6
Other Finding Aids
FA140 Rockefeller University records, President, Detlev W. Bronk, Administrative papers
FA914 Rockefeller University records, President, Detlev W. Bronk, General and Professional correspondence
FA965 Rockefeller University records, President, Detlev W. Bronk, Personal and Professional papers
Arrangement
The Rockefeller University records, President, Detlev W. Bronk materials are arranged into 4 components:
Administrative papers (FA140)
General and Professional correspondence (FA914)
Biographical and Personal material (FA964)
Personal and Professional papers (FA965)
See "other finding aids" note in this guide for directly links to the other Bronk holdings.
Conditions Governing Access note
Material is open for scholarly research.
RAC is unable to provide access to obsolete media and original digital media. In addition separated media may not yet have undergone stabilization procedures. When feasible, a digital surrogate may be created via special order. All applicable charges will apply. See RAC Head of Archival Services or RAC Head of Digital Programs for details.
Separated Materials
Audiovisual materials were separated from the body of the collection for specialized storage. Some formats are currently not playable inhouse at the RAC.
Biology -- Research; Medical sciences; Aviation medicine; Physiology; Operations management; Medical research; Bronk, Detlev W. (Detlev Wulf), 1897-1975; Unesco; Rockefeller University; National Research Council. (U.S.); Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research; National Science Foundation. (U.S.)
- Bibliographies (Box 1, Folder 1-6)
  - 1923-1976 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1923-1971 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1923-1939 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Additions to (those not in NAS list) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence re: Ruth Sternfeld. re: missing reprints, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Working copy. C. Kopp., 1981 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Biographical Memoirs (Box 1, Folder 7-11)
  - American Philosophical Society Yearbook. Britton Chance. photocopy., 1978 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - National Academy of Sciences, 1979, Vol. 50. Frank Brink, Jr. Reprint (Box 1, Folder 8-10)
  - Royal Society of London. Lord Adrian. 1976, Vol 22., photocopy. (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Obituaries (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Biographical Summaries (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Rockefeller University Public Information Biographies, 1972, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Bright, Mabel (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - "A Bouquet for Mabel Bright", 1978 November 27; Booklet.
  - N.A.S. Archives (Jean St. Clair), 1977. Enclosure, copy of letter from DWB/Lyman Chalkley, 1947 July 19., 1947, 1977
  - Mabel Bright/Paul Cranefield (and enclosures). Re: Preben Ramlov inquiry on relation between Jonas Bronk and DWB., 1981 September 3
- Bronk, Helen. Obituary news and notes., 1983 December-1984 January (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Bronk Fund. News and Notes., 1976 March (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Buildings Built/Dedicated by DWB (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Honors and Awards (Box 1, Folder 19)
- List of Lectures, 1926-1941 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Memberships (Box 1, Folder 21)
- The Rockefeller Institute/University (Box 1, Folder 22)
  Appraisal
  Correspondence re: salary information removed to Confidential files.
  - Copy of Report on the Committee on Nomination and Review, stencil, 15 pages.
  - Invitation from the Board of Trustees, RIMR, to meet Dr. and Mrs. Bronk, 1954 January 22
  - Edrick B. Smith/Bronk re: election as President and member of the Executive Committee, 1953 November 4 and 1954 October 21
  - Bronk/"Colleague", re: retirements, appointments, and changes in titles of departments/directorship, 1955 June 20
- RU Memorial, 1976 February 18 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  Scope and Contents
  Announcement; Booklet of printed recollections.
- Seitz, Frederick. A Tribute to DWB. Printed copy of presentation at Annual Meeting of the National Academy of Sciences, Washington, D.C., 1976 April 25 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Autobiographical Notes (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
  - ca. 1908-1960s (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Includes: diary.
  - Miscellaneous autobiographical notes (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Christmas Cards (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Clippings, 1920s, 1940s-1970s (Box 2, Folder 4-9)
- Correspondence, 1937-1939, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Personal Correspondence and Letters (Box 2, Folder 11-14)
  - 1926-1948 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - 1950-1959 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 1960-1969 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - 1970-1975 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Cranefield, Paul re: Science and Public Policy journal., 1977 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  Includes copy of Vol. 1, No. 1, 1964 July (only issue) with DWB note on cover.
- "Dictator" article. (Box 2, Folder 16-18)
  Friendship sloop owned by Alan M. Chesney.
  - Correspondence, c. 1952-1975 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Includes: Alan M. Chesney, William and Dorothy Tillett, R. Buckminster Fuller.
  - Manuscript, c. 1973 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Published article. DWB "Dictator, Marvelous Old Friendship Sloop Revived!" Ellsworth American, Ellsworth, ME, page 15., 1973 September 6 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    article contains photographs.
- Institute for Advanced Study. DWB note attached to copy of letter from John von Neumann/Lewis L. Strauss. Re: DWB and others as possible directors of Institute for Advanced Study., 1946 May 4 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Michigan, University of: Notifications of Appointments, 1924-1926 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Navy Department: 1935 correspondence re: DWB history of service, 1918-1922 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Notes, Drafts by DWB, c. 1925-1960 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  Includes: "Schedule", c. 1925, found in bound copy of DWB Ph.D. thesis; note attached to 1960 invitation to premiere of movie on Wernher von Braun.
- Personal, Miscellany (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Swathmore College: Transcript., 1917 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Photographs (Box 3)
  - Portraits (Box 3, Folder 1-4)
    - 1954 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - 1962 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Fortune Magazine, 1964 September (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Helen Bronk (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - DWB and David Rockefeller (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Group (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Vacation (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Interview with Daniel Greenberg, 1965 August 5 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence and Transcript, p. 1-29. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Transcript, p. 30-69. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Transcript, p. 70-103. (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Memorial Service at Rockefeller University (Tapes), 1976 February 18; Two 7" reels. (Box 4)
  Conditions Governing Access
  RAC is unable to provide access to obsolete media and original digital media. In addition separated media may not yet have undergone stabilization procedures. When feasible, a digital surrogate may be created via special order. All applicable charges will apply. See RAC Head of Archival Services or RAC Head of Digital Programs for details.
- Ph.D. Thesis, University of Michigan: An electrometric study of the submaxillary gland of the dog., 1925; 2 copies. (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
- Photographs (Box 6)
  - DWB Portraits: In college, 1925 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Cartoon: Wigodsky, Griffis, Bronk (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Family and early snapshots (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Detlev Bronk, c. 1899; 8x10 envelope.
    - Detlev Bronk (Swathmore)1, 1917; 8x10 envelope.
    - Detlev Bronk, c. 1914; 8x10 envelope.
    - Mitchell Bronk, John Bronk, Isabelle, 1921 September 10; 8x10 envelope.
    - D.W. Bronk house at Ann Arbor, 1921 (1921-1926)
    - Detlev Bronk, c. 1902; 8x10 envelope.
    - Detlev Bronk, c. 1904; 8x10 envelope.
    - Detlev Bronk, High School Graduation, 5x7 envelope.
  - Photographs: Group, 1940-1949 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - First Meeting of the Civilian Naval Research Advisory Committee., 1946 October 14
      ID of group photo on back.
    - American Scientific Advisory Group, first meeting, Tokyo, Japan, 1948 November 3
      ID of group on back.
    - Members of the Scientific Advisory Group greeted by Colonel J.S. Harbison on arrival at Haneda Airbase, Tokyo, Japan, 1948 November 28
  - Photographs: Group, 1950-1959 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Four year cost of training a medical student, 1950?; 2 photos.
    - Cost of Medical Education, 1900-1950; 1 photo.
      DWB in tuxedo.
    - D.W. Bronk with President Eisenhower, c. 1957 July 23; 2 photos.
  - Photographs: Group, 1960-1965 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - D.W. Bronk and Azuma, Governor of Tokyo, 1961 December; 2 photos.
    - D.W. Bronk and Clifford R. Gilliam. Swarthmore Alumni Issue., 1962 October; 1 clipping. 1 print.
    - D.W. Bronk accepting award of 1964 Golden Jubilee Award of the Golden Age Club, at Our Lady of Mercy Church, Bronx, NY, 1965 April 5
  - Photographs: Group, 1970-1975 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Governor's Committee on Scholastic Acheivement, The Pierre Hotel, New York City. D.W. Bronk and Frederick Seitz, 1973 June 21; 1 photo.
    - National Academy of Sciences 111th Meeting, Washington, D.C. Wallace Harrison, the Bronks, Jean St. Clair., 1974 April 22; 3 prints.
  - Photographs: Group, undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - D.W. Bronk in tuxedo with others.
      Photographer: Dick Clayton.
    - WAAM photograph. D.W. Bronk at left.
    - U.S. Army photographs. D.W. Bronk standing., 2 photos.
    - D.W. Bronk standing, second from right., One 8x10, one 5x7.
      Photographer: Shreve Ballard, Santa Barbara, CA.
    - D.W. Bronk seated third from left.
      Photographer: Harris & Ewing, Washington, D.C.
    - D.W. Bronk in striped tie., 6 photographs.
    - D.W. Bronk, H.S. Gasser and unidentified others
    - WAAM Program Advisory Council meeting. In first photo D.W. Bronk seated first right side., 4 photos.
  - Photographs: Group, undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - D.W. Bronk to left., 2 photos, 5x7 envelope.
    - General Carl A. Spaatz presenting the Emblem for Exceptional Civilian to D.W. Bronk, 6 photos.
    - D.W. Bronk at podium., 1 photo.
    - D.W. Bronk row 4, fourth from left., 1 photo, color.
    - D.W. Bronk identified in first group photo., 14 photos.
    - D.W. Bronk in center receiving medal.
  - D.W. Bronk: Informal (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - At LaGuardia Airport boarding plane to London to deliver Croonian Lecture at Royal Society on June 30, 1949., 1949 June 27
      Includes newspaper clippings and press release.
    - Different poses, 1957 October 2
  - Photographs: Honorary Degrees, Awards (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - D.W. Bronk and E.D. Adrian receiving honorary D.Sc. from University of Pennsylvania, 1931 October 13
    - D.W. Bronk in center. Inscribed "To Dr. Detlev Bronk with Best wishes, Harold E. Stassen", 1949 June
    - D.W. Bronk giving address, "Science in a Democracy" at Yale School Auditorium, 75th Anniversary celebration of Connecticut Agricultural Experiment Station, 8 pm., 1950 September 28; 1 photo.
    - General Electric Company., Schenectady, NY. D.W. Bronk in center., 1950 October 11
      General News Bureau photo.
    - Honorary Degree Candidates, New York University., 1951 September 15; 1 photo.
    - D.W. Bronk, President, NAS, extends greetings from the Learned Socities of the U.S. to the USMA Cadets and Guests, Jubilee Banquet in the Washington Hall, USMA, West Point New York; Commemorating 150th Anniversary of the military academy. D.W. Bronk at Podium, 1952 May 20
    - Graduation of Submarine School officers class, D.W. Bronk guest speaker, U.S. Naval submarine base, New London, CT., 1952 June 13; 2 photos.
      1 photo has D.W. Bronk at podium.
    - D.W. Bronk and others, Adams, MA, undated
      Photo by Vrabel Studio.
    - Grinnel College News Service, Grinnel. IA.: D.W. Bronk and others., undated
    - University of Michigan News Service, Ann Arbor, MI: D.W. Bronk receiving honorary degree., undated
    - D.W. Bronk and others., undated
      Photographer: John A. Kelly Jr.
    - University of Cincinnati: L to R: Dr. Martin H. Fischer, D.W. Bronk, Dr. William T. Semple, undated
    - Baltimore, MD. 1: D.W. Bronk to left. 2: D.W. Bronk in center., undated; 2 photos.
      Photographer: Sussman-Ochs.
    - Outdoors. D.W. Bronk last row, third from right., undated; 1 photo.
    - D.W. Bronk presenting degree, undated; 5 photos.
    - undated, 1 photo.
    - undated, 1 photo.
  - Photographs: Honorary Degrees, Awards (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - D.W. Bronk, President (?), awarding honorary degrees to Schmidt, Dr. Hill, E.D. Adrian and unidentified others, outside of Jenkins Hall, Johns Hopkins University., undated; 14 photos, some duplicates.
    - D.W. Bronk awarding honorary degree to unidentified person (possibly Flexner), undated
    - Miscellaneous photos, undated; 7 photos.
  - Photographs: Honorary Degrees, Awards (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Group photo: Inscription on back "From J.S. Bixler, Colby, College", undated; 1 photo.
    - One recipient of honorary degree, identified as Henry Allen Moe., 7 photos.
      Photographer: Sussman-Ochs, Baltimore, MD.
    - Evening celebration, undated; 2 photos.
      Photographer: Sussman-Ochs, Baltimore, MD
    - Appears to be Notre Dame, undated; 5 photos.
    - Degree granting, undated; 2 photos.
    - D.W. Bronk wearing tuxedo, undated; 2 photos.
    - D.W. Bronk receiving honorary degree, Brooklyn, NY (?), undated; 3 photos.
      One photo includes Mrs. Helen Bronk, D.W. Bronk and others.
  - Photographs: Johns Hopkins University, President (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Bowman and new President, D.W. Bronk, 1 photo.
      Photographer: Garrett.
    - Bowman, D.W. Bronk and Carlyle Barton (?), 1 photo.
  - Photographs: Johnson Foundation (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Interior of D.W. Bronk's office at the Johnson Foundation, 1 photo.
    - Johnson Foundation Directory, 1945 December, 1946 December; 2 photos.
  - Photographs: National Advisory for Aeronautics (NACA) (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - National Advisory Committee for Aeronautics, members., 1950 September 1
      Composite photo.
    - National Advisory Committee for Aeronautics, meeting, 1952 December
      ID on back of photo.
  - Photographs: Rockefeller University (RU) (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Convocation, undated; 5x7 envelope.
      some identification on back of photo.
    - undated, color snapshots, 5x7 envelope
    - At celebrations, Five photos, 5x7, b&w
      some identification
    - First Rockefeller University graduate students
    - Convocation, D.W. Bronk, Vannevar Bush and David Rockefeller. Bush recipient honorary D.Sc., 1967
    - Mabel Bright in her office, Caspary Hall.
    - Gardener at RU, watering lawn, 1961 July
  - Photographs: Scientists and Colleagues (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Otto Meyherhof in A.V. Hill's garden, 1921; 1 photo.
    - Rio. Paul Krebs (?), 1960; 1 photo.
    - unidentified, 4 photos.
  - Photographs: Woods Hole Trustees (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Group, undated; 1 photo.
      with accompanying identification.
    - Group at annual meeting of the Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution., 1966 June 23; 1 photo.
    - Group at annual meeting of the Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution., 1970 June 19; 1 photo, in color.
    - Group, undated; 1 photo, color.
  - Photographs: Unidentified (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - "Pictures of Academy", 6 photos in envelope.
      Photographer: AMB
    - Sand formations (?), 1 photo.
- Slides (Box 7)
  - Rose Tree Hunt Speech, "Memoirs of a Fox Hunting Gentleman", 1964 February 24 (Box 7)